Next up we have Christian Newman for the last - for the hour here - who's going to talk about how
we can craft strong identifier names. Christian - educate us!
All right - can you all hear me?
Perfect. Great.
So my name is Christian I'm the head researcher at the SCANL laboratory,
so if you enjoy what we talk about today please feel free to visit our website which you can find
at the bottom of this slide scanl.org. So today I wanted to talk to
you about identifier names, and so on this slide you see several
different types of identifiers, some of them have one or
two different words in them, some of them have prepositions,
but a lot of them probably seem a little familiar to you
because you've probably seen identifiers that look like these
or perhaps even identifiers that look exactly like these
and I want you to keep that in the back of your mind as we're talking
because we're going to discuss why some of these look familiar to you as we go through.
So one question I wanted to ask about these is, well, are they good identifiers?
And if we kind of scan back here you'll probably look at this list,
you'll say, ah maybe, you know it depends,
like, you look at the code and
you might come to some conclusion, but the point here is that
we would have to talk about it. As developers we'd have to perform code reviews,
we'd have to look at the code, we'd have to come to some collective
conclusion about the quality of these. And so I think identifier naming is
at least partially subjective - it depends on the person that's
reading it and on the code context and what the person is trying to convey.
There's no objective quality metric for what makes a high-quality identifier.
But we've all seen it, right, so everybody's looked at some
code and they've been like, ah, this - I don't - I don't know what this is doing,
why did they do it that way, what does PCL mean,
why is this a single letter, I don't understand what this is
I hate Hungarian, why are they using Hungarian,
why is there an alphabet in front of my identifier.
So we know bad identifiers when we see it, even if we don't always know exactly why it's
bad or what makes it a bad identifier, we've all seen something that just made
us kind of, you know, cringe. So a metric or some way of being
able to understand the quality of these would be very useful.
It could tell us - instead of us having to talk about it we could look at the metric
and the metric says, hey, you know, this is good, and it
could give us some reasons for why it's good, and we might you know look at those and say,
okay, I understand why it's named that way now, it makes sense, okay, great.
Unfortunately, making a metric for this is very difficult, right.
There are different - and one of the big reasons for this is that there are different perspectives
that each identifier has to satisfy. You could be talking to a student or an
expert or a senior developer and each of these groups
needs a different kind of identifier. A senior understands the idioms and the - and the
terminology and the different grammatical structure of
identifiers that software engineers use, whereas a student has never seen it before.
And I want you to pay attention to that because students don't understand the
language of software development whereas a senior does,
and there's something important there, because what I'm saying here is that we've
created a language for ourselves internal to the software development community,
which is how we convey the meaning of software to one another.
And people outside of that community don't understand what we're talking about using this,
even though they might speak the same human languages we do so -
they might all speak English but they don't understand what we're talking about.
But program comprehension is critically important. It's the thing that we have to
do before you do anything else. If you're going to add a feature,
if you're going to fix a bug, you need to understand the software.
So we actually really should be paying attention to this - to this phenomenon.
Okay, so what makes this hard? Well over the course of of decades,
we as developers have created this sub-language and the sub-language,
which is based on a human language - so for a lot of us that would be English
but it can be other human languages as well - and this sub-language specializes English into
certain grammatical phrases and idioms that we use to describe software -
to describe the behavior of software. On top of that,
this is 70% of the code, so if you look at the characters in the code,
70% of all characters in the code are an identifier,
and so if you don't understand that sub-language that we're using then you
don't understand the code, you can't read it,
it's a foreign language too essentially. And we - and the other thing to realize
here is that we didn't design this language but we did create it, right,
so as developers we all evolved this language over time to deal with historical contexts.
So for example, old languages used
to limit the number of characters that you could use to - just to to create a variable.
This forced us to have to use much shorter speech to say the same amount of text that you would
say in a sentence, right. So we created this but
we didn't design it up front - we didn't come up with its rules,
we had to evolve it to to deal with our jobs and our - and our education.
So the thing that my lab is trying to do is study this sub-language,
to understand what are the rules that we have collectively curated over
time so that we can make the rules explicit, so that everybody understands what they are,
find ways to measure and describe the effect that these rules have on
comprehension for different types of readers, so for novices versus experts, for example,
and use this understanding to create better name creation, appraisal, and maintenance approaches.
So I wanted to talk to you today about one particular approach
and that's an approach that my lab has been studying a lot lately,
which is grammar patterns. The way that you get a grammar
pattern is you take an identifier - so you can see two on the screen here -
you apply a splitter - the splitter splits these
identifiers into their constituent words - and then you apply a part-of-speech tagger that
is specialized for the context of software, because remember,
because software follows a different grammatical structure,
you can't just take it off the shelf part-of-speech tagger
you you need to use specialized NLP techniques to deal with these things.
And what we did was, we did a study where we took a lot
of code and we looked through how this code - or we looked at the identifier name
structure for all this code, so we collected a bunch of
grammar patterns and we looked at how they were being used in the software,
and so I want to take a quick look at this. If you scan down in this little catalog,
what we did was we basically took the taxonomy and we
listed out every single pattern that we found. So these are grammatical structures.
So the first one here is a noun phrase. What a noun phrase is, is a sequence of
noun modifiers followed by a head noun. And so we can see examples of that down
here where we have the head noun "label". The head noun typically represents what
the - what the entity - what the variable actually is trying to convey in the code,
and then the words that come to the left, the noun modifiers, are descriptive,
so they function as adjectives. In fact noun modifiers are what
we call noun adjuncts, which are effectively
nouns that are posing as adjectives. And so in this case what we have is a label
that is specifically a selection width label, so this is a descriptive of the type
of label that we're talking about. If we go down we'll see prepositional phrases.
Prepositional phrases tend to be identifiers that deal with, for example, conversion,
so converting to a string or performing some kind of an event,
so, like, "on click", "on button press", that kind of stuff,
and so what I want you to kind of get, since we don't have enough time
to go through all of these, is that different patterns correlate
to different types of behavior in the software. And so really what we're looking at here is a
glimpse of this sub-language that I've been kind of talking about up to this point.
We've created these patterns of speech that allow us to convey behavior very quickly to one another
without having to be very explicit about what - what nuances there are under the
text - there's a lot of subtext here. And so these are some of the basic
natural language phrasal structures that we as developers have created over the
last 50-100 years or whatever. So what we did with these is,
we created a little bit of a tool - this is just kind of an initial way to
start trying to address the problem - and what this tool does is,
it looks at the grammar patterns in your code
and it looks at some of the some of the surrounding code
and it gives you a recommendation. So in this case we have the variable "characters".
Our tool sees that the type of this is singular so it's character,
and it's recommending that you not use a plural, but instead use a singular noun,
so basically make this "character" singular instead of "characters".
And so that's just a quick example of what this tool does.
And note here that it gives examples of what it's talking about when it gives these patterns,
and also an explanation, which are two things that we think are
very, very important for these types of tools. So our goal for this work in the future is to
fully explore the diversity of grammar patterns, so we - there are more of these,
we want to find out how many of these exist so that we can again make them explicit.
We want to create data-driven naming guidelines, so this is sets of measurements that can look at
different aspects of the identifier name - does it contain abbreviations,
does it contain domain terminology, etc. And we want to make these so that we can
understand how they affect the human reading it, because if - because again,
if you don't understand who is trying to read the code then you can't give a metric that tells
you how easy it is for them to read it. If I don't know who's looking at this
then I can't tell you if this is a good identifier for them or not.
And then we want to create a framework that optimizes,
or that helps us optimize names - that prioritizes the reader and explainability.
So another core tenant to this is that if you can't explain to people why this is
good or bad or what is good or bad about it then they can't make good decisions about
whether this is a recommendation that they should be taking.
So if we just give them a black box that tells them what the best thing is they won't be able
to tell me if this is good or bad because they don't know why the box
is recommending that - that particular pattern to them.
And so then our last goal is obviously educating developers at all levels about this language
so that they can correctly express themselves when they're -
so they can express themselves as optimally as possible to others when they're writing code.
And so that's the end of my presentation. If you're, again, if you're interested,
you can visit our website at scanl.org, the little QR code takes you to
our - the name structure catalog which also contains links to papers in our webpage
if you're - if you're looking to find those. And that's it - thank you.